<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<appendix> <title> Project history </title>

  <sect1> <title> VIA and the Network2000 project </title>

    <para>
The whole project started back in 1995. At that time, students of the
<ulink url="http://www.ecp.fr/"> &Eacute;cole Centrale de Paris </ulink>
enjoyed a TokenRing network, managed by the <ulink
url="http://www.via.ecp.fr/"> VIA Centrale R&eacute;seaux
association</ulink>, and were looking
for a solution to upgrade to a modern network. So the idea behind
Network2000 was to find a project students would realize that would
be interesting, would require a high-quality network, and could
provide enough fame so that sponsors would be interested.
    </para>

    <para>
Someone came up with the idea of doing television broadcast on the
network, so that students could watch TV in their room. This was
interesting, mixed a lot of cool technologies, and provided fame
because no one had written a free MPEG-2 decoder so far.
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title> Foundation of the VideoLAN project </title>

    <para>
<ulink url="http://www.3com.com/"> 3Com</ulink>,
<ulink url="http://www.bouygues.com/"> Bouygues </ulink> and
la Soci&eacute;t&eacute; des Amis were
interested and financed the project, which was then known after
the name of VideoLAN.
    </para>

    <para>
The VideoLAN team, in particular <ulink url="mailto:walken@via.ecp.fr">
Michel Lespinasse </ulink> (current maintainer of <ulink
url="http://www.linuxvideo.org/">LiViD</ulink>'s mpeg2dec)
and <ulink url="mailto:hpreg@via.ecp.fr"> R&eacute;gis
Duchesne</ulink>, started writing code in 1996. By the end of 1997 they had
a working client-server solution, but it would crash a lot and was
hard to extend.
    </para>

    <para>
At that time it was still closed-source and only-for-demo code.
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title> VLC media player design </title>

    <para>
In 1998, <ulink url="mailto:seguin@via.ecp.fr"> Vincent Seguin</ulink>
(structure, interface and video output),
<ulink url="mailto:massiot@via.ecp.fr"> Christophe Massiot</ulink>
(input and video decoder),
<ulink url="mailto:maxx@via.ecp.fr"> Michel Kaempf</ulink>
(audio decoder and audio output) and
<ulink url="mailto:polux@via.ecp.fr"> Jean-Marc Dressler</ulink>
(synchronization) decided to write a brand new player from scratch,
called VideoLAN Client (VLC), so that it could be easily open sourced.
Of course we based it on code written by our predecessors, but in
an advanced structure, described in the first chapter (it hasn't been
necessary to change it a lot).
    </para>

    <para>
At the same time, <ulink url="mailto:benny@via.ecp.fr"> Beno&icirc;t
Steiner </ulink> started the writing of an advanced stream server, called
VideoLAN Server (VLS).
    </para>

    <para>
Functional test seeds have been released internally in June 1999
(vlc-DR1) and November 1999 (vlc-DR2), and we started large scale tests
and presentations. The French audience discovered us at Linux Expo
in June 1999, presenting our 20 minutes of Golden Eye (which is now
a legend among developers :-).  At that time only a network input was
possible, file input was added later, but it remained kludgy for a while.
    </para>

    <para>
In early 2000, we (especially <ulink url="mailto:sam@via.ecp.fr"> Samuel
Hocevar</ulink>, who is still a major contributor) started working
on DVDs (PS files, AC3, SPU). In the summer 2000, pre-release builds
have been seeded (0.2.0 versions), but they still lacked essential
features.
    </para>

    <para>
In late 2000, <ulink url="mailto:massiot@via.ecp.fr"> Christophe Massiot
</ulink> with the support of his company,
<ulink url="http://www.idealx.com/"> IDEALX</ulink>, rewrote major
parts of the input to allow modularization and advanced navigation, and <ulink
url="mailto:stef@via.ecp.fr"> Stéphane Borel </ulink> worked on a
fully-featured DVD plug-in for VLC.
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1> <title> The Opening </title>

    <para>
For Linux Expo in February 2001, the <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/">
Free Software Foundation </ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.idealx.com/">
IDEALX </ulink> wanted to make live streaming of the 2001 FSF awards
from Paris to New York. VideoLAN was the chosen solution. Finally
it couldn't be done live because of bandwidth considerations, but a
<ulink url="http://www.via.ecp.fr/~massiot/encoding.html"> chain of 
fully open-source solutions </ulink> made it possible to record it.
    </para>

    <para>
At the same time, the president of the <ulink url="http://www.ecp.fr/">
&Eacute;cole Centrale Paris</ulink> officially decided to place the software
under GNU General Public Licence, thanks to <ulink
url="mailto:henri@via.ecp.fr"> Henri Fallon</ulink>, <ulink
url="mailto:jprey@ads.ecp.fr"> Jean-Philippe Rey</ulink>, and the IDEALX team.
    </para>

    <para>
VideoLAN software is now one of the most popular open source DVD
players available, and has contributors all around the world. The
last chapter of this appendix is not written yet :-).
    </para>

  </sect1>

</appendix>
